so you have a young person and when I
was a school teacher this was the case
who expressed the desire to be an
astrophysicist
and the teacher says to them that's a
great idea but actually I think you'd be
really good at sport
I think you'd be really good at sport I
think you've got a better chance of
doing that now that throwing off the
scent
if that message is repetitively relayed
over a five-year period from year seven
to year 11 or from 11 to 16. well what
do you think you're going to do when
you're when you're 16 years of age
you've been thrown completely off the
scent of something that you potentially
could have done and I think that this
happens
a lot with children from minoritized
groups and children
particularly beneath the poverty line
[Music]
to change the world I'm Christian Guru
Murphy and this is the podcast in which
we talk to extraordinary people about
ideas and the events that have helped
shape them
my guest this week Jason our day is
remarkable for all sorts of reasons he
is under 40 and he's a professor at
Cambridge University which makes him
extraordinary as a young black man for a
start what's even more extraordinary
about him is that when he was three he
was diagnosed with autism he didn't
speak a word until he was 11. the
experts told his mother that he would
struggle with living an ordinary life in
the big wide world and yet he has
achieved extraordinary amounts of things
and written books and and excelled in
Academia Jason thank you very much for
joining us oh Christian thank you so
much homie here so your story is really
very inspiring and you've done TED talks
about it and um and you speak very
fluently
but
it was not always like this no it wasn't
I mean that's the crazy irony but I
guess what I was very fortunate
um to have in that kind of that period
of where there was I guess a paralysis
of speech was the ability to observe to
understand the human interaction to
understand how people use dialect
verbal non-verbal kind of interactions
to engage with people and I guess it
kind of all came to a
to a crescendo at 11 and it all kind of
made sense and it's quite ironic that
having
um in some respects been dumb as a child
in a literal sense that um as an adult
now I I speak to people for a living in
some way shape or form and and were you
treated
dumb
um I I was um in the literal centers
somebody who's dumb who is not able to
speak
um and then there's the kind of societal
framing that we have and the kind of
demonstrative use of that word
um which was which you're kind of
categorized as not being particularly
intelligent or not able and so that
there's that aspect of it as well which
is also challenging when people use a
word like that in the wrong context to
demean or to kind of disrespect people
and I guess that was part of my
existence growing up so what were you
diagnosed with because autism covers
yeah yeah it comes a range of things so
in old money I was diagnosed with
Asperger's Syndrome which is commonly
now referred to as autism so you know
Spectrum disorders something that is
looking to be kind of disbanded in many
respects because actually autism is the
context more generally and I was
diagnosed with global development delay
when I was um just before I turned three
so which is kind of a cognitive and
motor skills development sort of
disorder order in terms of being able to
read particular milestones and so
there's a delay or for my in my
particular case there was a delay in how
my brain processes information which was
very very slow so what's I mean what do
you remember of those early years when
you were not speaking
and were you reading no no so I didn't
learn to read until I was an adult so I
was 18 when I um just just turned 18
when I learned to read and write so what
do you remember about communication
power of observation and non-verbal and
you know my mum often kind of pointing
to cues in terms of how people interact
with one another so for example
something like a hug or a handshake why
is that symbolic you know how do you
engage with people through the means of
non-communication what does a smile
represent what does a wave represent all
these kind of different things in these
different social cues from which we
develop relationships and human
interaction one another and for me it
was the best education I could have had
because those observations would be
hugely important to me as I kind of
traversed adolescence my teenage years
and then subsequently when I became an
adult and went to University all of
those things I'd observed as a young
child I I then had a playground to put
them into use and I think the deficit
approach or the deficit way of thinking
can be that I must have been hugely
disadvantaged yes there are
disadvantages of course but one of the
things that was really important was
that I was able to make sense of the
world in a completely unique way and
actually what it did emphasize to me is
that human beings by their very nature
the power to do great and wonderful
things and observing that in Technicolor
without the audio so to speak is quite
an interesting thing do you think it's
made you better at reading people
exactly yeah massively it also it also
allows me not to make too many judgments
on people and actually listen and I
always kind of think there's a there's a
real difference between listening and
being heard
and one of the things you do in that
state of of paralysis in terms of speech
in some respects you spend a lot of time
listening to people but do you have any
understanding of what actually happens
to enable you to suddenly speak I'd be
lying if I said I did
um I mean what I would say is that with
a learning development with a
developmental delay there is this
cognitive thing where something is
happening now what I would say is that
for
someone like myself who's neurodivergent
and who has and who has autism and
Global development they did the key
thing for somebody that may have that is
repetition
and doing the same thing over and over
and over again is probably going to be
quite a likely way to unlock something
that almost may be Jarred how
how to
read and write and speak from the age of
11.
do you get to University entrance at the
same time as everybody else I went to
University when I was 20. so
um I was very fortunate that I I had a
tutor at college named Sandro Sandry you
know I went to University at 20 but I
had the reading age of a nine-year-old
you know so you you're trying to really
kind of really I mean is that possible
yeah it is yeah I mean what what is
interesting is that there are a lot of
mechanisms at universities to support
people
and so when I went to University a lot
of it was trial and error how do you
account for for getting
to that point where you got into
University because that in itself is a
huge achievement is that is that you
being incredibly driven is that your mum
kicking you down the road every day is
it your tutor I I think it was all of
the above it's kind of all of the above
I I really strongly believe in this
concept and I think Muhammad Ali was
kind of the first one to kind of really
talk about it and he spoke about this
idea of will versus skill
now I don't have any
skill
um but what I do have is an indomitable
will and I knew that I had one or two
things I was good at and I was going to
drive that as much as I could and I knew
that the will to succeed and the
discipline and the sacrifice I was
willing to make may actually be a
difference in terms of me just being
able to hang so I'll always be punching
above my weight but just being able to
step in the ring and go a few rounds
like that's what I wanted to do and I
always thought that at some point I'm
going to be a 12 round fighter I don't
believe there is a person on this planet
who doesn't not have talent because I I
genuinely believe everybody's life has
purpose I'm obsessed with this idea of
purpose I have been from a very very
young age and I believe everybody's life
has meaning and everybody's life has
purpose and everyone is on this Earth to
fulfill that purpose have you found your
purpose
I was very fortunate to know what my
purpose was from a very young age
my mother took me to a homeless shelter
when I was 18
um at Christmas when I went there
um I met a gentleman and as it happened
not that I knew what one was at the time
but he was a professor he had been a
professor and he explained to me a
Christian that anyone can end up in this
situation and that he was a person of
esteem you know he had a professorship I
had a wife had children and he said that
my wife and children died in a road
accident and as a result I became
depressed and became destitute I turned
to certain levers should we say to help
me get me through those times and then
as a result lost connection with reality
they said Jason I know you're here for a
few hours but the thing I would like you
to take away from this is that people
don't just end up here by their own
relation there are circumstances that
can impact how people's life turn out
and so when you see someone that may be
homeless or you see someone that may be
in need never make a judgment that they
have somehow brought themselves to this
situation always work from the position
of empathy and I'd obviously have that
as a foregrounding in my upbringing but
having that particular moment
I would go as far as to say it was the
most important four hours of my life and
when I got back home I knew exactly what
my purpose was and so I threw myself
into charity work
and realized probably at some point in
my mid-20s maybe a little later on that
I could probably utilize education as a
vehicle to really penetrate the walls of
policy to change the kind of inequality
that I I have I had observed throughout
my life you know the drive and the
single-mindedness and the determination
the cliche
um maybe is a misunderstanding of
somebody with autism would be well that
that kind of must feed that a little bit
you know that there's an obsessive trait
within autism is that true is that is
that true for you I I think it's a
it's a myth and a stereotype that's
endured and it's probably been kind of
crystallized by kind of
films Like Rain Man and Dustin Hoffman's
portrayal of an autistic person and this
obsession with numbers
um I think for myself and I can never
speak for myself
there is no doubt that my autism and the
repetitive aspects of that
um which are hugely useful
um in many respects have been incredibly
useful to me well well I mean the the
other myth you perhaps bust
for somebody with autism is is talking
about empathy because again the other
the other sort of cliche and perhaps
it's misunderstanding again is well you
know if you've got autism then
you find empathy difficult yeah and I
think again it's it's a stereotype and a
myth that's endured
um is it a stereotype or a myth it's a
myth because a stereotype is usually
based on truth there's no yeah sometimes
um sometimes I mean
for example there are stereotypes that
exist across a myriad of intersections
which for me are just not true but that
particular myth I I think is one that's
not true and I think actually it's been
very dangerous to the autistic Community
because in some respects there's always
been this idea that well you don't
understand empathy they don't you know
that this coldness there's this kind of
absence of feeling and the problem with
that particular myth is it actually
delegitimizes how autistic people may
feel about certain things so actually a
better way of thinking about it is that
people demonstrate and show empathy in
different ways
do you think we're getting better as a
society at dealing with or understanding
neurodiversity I think so I think so I
think there's still a lot of
conversations that need to be had I
think there's conversations in terms of
how we focus on providing better
resource and access and information
particularly to the carers and parents
of neurodivergent children and as a
society we need to really do more to
disrupt these neurotypical binaries that
in many respects ostracize
neurodivergent people in the
neurodivergent community and I think we
are having those conversations I think
we've we've matured in our conversations
I think we're moving away from you know
what was in some respects very deficit
language about the neurodivergent
community and individuals with
disability what do you mean by deficit
language
I think there was always a language of
can't do there was always a language of
um not quite as able not intellectually
as capable and it's again it's it's it's
framing it's very much situated in this
idea that there's only one form of
intellect there's only one form of
things that we actually deem of value
there are many forms of intellect there
are many forms of intelligence and I
think we're beginning to break that
binary and have you know more mature
conversations about what does that mean
so how how do you become you know how do
you get to be one of the youngest
professors
um in Cambridge the youngest black
professor
um in Cambridge yeah I mean it's really
interesting I mean funnily enough the
charity stuff in some respects is easier
so I would I would never Proclaim that
my research per se
um is going to change the world but what
does change the world is the actions
behind that research so the Praxis
element so there's this Theory element
but then there's this practice element
and putting that theory or those
recommendations into practice is where
you want to really penetrate the
inequality that exists structurally so
what is your discipline
good question so my discipline is
technically I'm professor of Sociology
of education and my main focus is on
kind of intersectional inequality with a
particular focus on racial inequality in
education and particularly higher
education and one of the things I I
focus on or I have focused on a lot
is really the inequitable structures
that um disrupt or prohibit black and
ethnic minority people from progressing
in education more generally and
particularly in higher education
that I mean one of the basic problems
with Oxbridge is that there are very
very few black people yeah who are
either as students or as
professors or teachers or fellows
um so how how you know how do you break
that how did you break that were you a
special case do people treat you
differently because yeah of your you
know your unusual upbringing and your
route through education
um so I've got a special pass yeah no I
I definitely didn't I mean um
I I was particularly dedicated
um and also as it's kind of been widely
reported uh in 2012 I I had written the
list of goals and one of them was I was
going to work at Oxford Cambridge now in
2012 I was still teaching PE so there
was no way that you know anyone can
really apart from in my mind's eye
you have that as an ambition but even I
probably my wildest dreams didn't know I
would realize that if I'm being honest
um but just because you knew they were
the best or no not because yeah it's
more because I just thought how
ridiculous would it be that you know
someone like myself could end up in a
place like that in terms of how I got
there
I mean look part of it is that yes I
I've worked extremely hard I'm
academically in that sense capable and
I've satisfied all the criteria to be in
that situation but to be honest with you
Christian
um
there are a lot of exceptional academics
out there particularly black and ethnic
minority academics who are if not just
as deserving possibly more deserving and
a huge thing that you can't compensate
for in life
is luck
sometimes you just get lucky sometimes
you're in the right place at the right
time and that Arc of Destiny
can be marked by luck and you know as Al
Pacino famously said in Any Given Sunday
life being this game of inches you know
and when it mattered
those inches when when in my favor so so
as well as luck
you're saying that there are structural
reasons oh no they're so what are they
well the structural reasons I mean the
first thing would be institutional
racism you know that that's the first
thing and I think it penetrates all of
our major institutions within Society
you know the police force the Judiciary
you know education
NHS all those things and
72 of the British population or over 70
of the British population consider
themselves to be for a working class
background and we have systems and
structures in place that hugely
disadvantage people from working class
backgrounds in Britain
and there have been several whining
participation interventions over the
last 10 20 years within the higher
education sector that have sought to
reduce that Gap but we still have a huge
way to go in providing that Equitable
space and doing that and I guess those
inequalities for me they ring true
because I meet people every day who will
say to me I'm the first of my family to
go to university and you kind of think
about okay what are the implications of
that how do you break that
intergenerational bind of inequality so
what are the structural things that you
want to break that are the causes
because a lot you know a lot of people
don't believe this you know they just
kind of think this is
um you know special pleading from a
group of people who are struggling and
they're struggling for all sorts of
reasons because yeah you know of early
early education and Community poverty
and all those sorts of things and that
it just takes time you know the old
pipeline argument that it takes time for
people to make their way down the
pipeline to get get to the top so what
do you mean by institutional racism and
what are the structural barriers so the
structural barriers are um we're really
talking about access to information and
access to it
um education and part of that it's
actually how we view particular groups
of people in society so for example
working class children children of white
working class children children of color
individuals with disability you know
just just as an example across the
myriad
we have these particular fixed views on
these individuals and part of what my
work looks or attempts to do is to
really think about how we change
mindsets so the so for example
racial profiling
has a huge implication on black brown
and ethnic minority children you know in
terms of the expectations that teachers
have of those pupils that then kind of
go through this educational journey into
you know further education in higher
education those implicate those kind of
views that those teachers have really
shape that individual's educational
experience in terms of what they can
aspirationally do and what they can't do
so I often refer to it my work as
throwing people off the scent so you
have a young person and when I was a
school teacher this was the case who
expressed a desire to be an
astrophysicist
and the teacher says to them that's a
great idea but actually I think you'd be
really good at sport
I think you'd be really good at sport I
think you've got a better chance of
doing that now that throwing off the
scent
if that message is repetitively relayed
over a five-year period from year seven
to year 11 or from 11 to 16. well what
do you think you're going to do when
you're when you're 16 years of age
you've been thrown completely off the
scent of something that you potentially
could have done and I think that this
happens
a lot with children from minoritized
groups and children
particularly beneath the poverty line
and I think that's something that I in
terms of kind of a brief synopsis of
those structural things I think that's
really really important and then you
have this kind of profiling again that
happens in terms of how the police
engage with young black people as an
example and how that profiling is quite
demonstrative in terms of
this idea that you know black people
potentially are aggressive they're
dangerous you know there's a
vilification of black people within
Britain that is problematic okay so so
Russia sooner called kirst armor call
you in and they say all right what do
you want to do what do you want to
change
the thing that I'd want to change is I'd
want to find a way of democratizing
resource to those most in need
I still feel that those most in need
I feel there's so many kind of
there's so much effort in my opinion
placed into ensuring that those
individuals are most in need don't get
access to the help and support they need
we have this weird thing in society
where
that there's almost accountability among
some parliamentarians to sit and to
watch people struggle
you know um this idea that they have
this altruistic view that we all want to
help the world
sometimes sometimes I wonder and you
know if we think about the government
that we have
in in kind of Premiership now
you know one of the things I always
think is are any of you moved by empathy
do you see what's happening around you
do you see the difficulties that people
are facing do you see the struggles that
people are encountering
from day to day
and you kind of think if you could just
park your infighting for two minutes and
just actually observe what's going on
around you you may realize that actually
there are a lot of people suffering in
your job as a public servant is to serve
the public to the best of your ability
and to ensure that you do the best you
can for society
and at the moment what we have in some
respects is several parliamentarians in
this current government that abdicating
that responsibility
but I mean that's a very big Global idea
that you're talking about in terms of
getting resource to the people who need
it and you could deliver that through
a benefit system or through Socialism or
through all you know all sorts of
different ways you could think of but
but your work is in education and in
structural inequality in education how
do you solve structural inequality in
education the question I think the way
you solve structural inequality in
education for me is to really think
about what the problems are so what are
the nature of the problems what are the
root of the problems and for me a huge
part of that is recognizing aspects of
the curriculum in terms of how do we
broaden the curriculum to be more
reflective of a multicultural
multi-ethnic multi-diverse
society which by the way I think that
we're making slow inroads into that
which I think is hugely important and
that's penetrating primary schools
secondary further and higher education
so I think that's a really good thing I
think one of the things that's kind of
really important in terms of those
educational inequalities is really
thinking about
those individuals who particularly come
from families where people are living
below the breadline and how that impacts
their educational trajectories and
aspirations and I think there needs to
be a lot more done which by the way
like there's things I can do as well in
terms of in the in the very privileged
position that I now find myself in to
really find ways to
not only create and develop manifestos
and a census around what needs to be
done but really to kind of
engage parliamentarians in some of the
processes that they could potentially
engage in to ensure that actually people
have a better understanding of what
those difficulties are when I say better
understanding I mean particularly
parliamentarians because I don't always
think they're aware of some of those
educational struggles
so you're a professor of Cambridge now
Cambridge has made a big deal of trying
to address
the structural inequality of of the
schools that it's undergraduates come
from and it's and it's done a lot you
know the intake of Cambridge now is you
know overwhelmingly from State schools
um even if private schools get a
disproportionate number of yeah kids in
um how meritocratic do you think it is
now in terms of who gets in
that's a great question you've stumped
me middle stump there
um is it meritocratic I think it's
working towards becoming that way I I
think it's actually an issue for the
sector more broadly actually
particularly
um you know
in the Russell group institutions
um who
don't engage
civically as much as the post-92
institutions do who really have that
whining participation
Mantra deeply into woven in the things
that they do in terms of particularly
getting opportunities people to access
University that may not have always had
the opportunity I think that um the idea
of meritocracy if I'm being absolutely
honest I think in in theory it's a
brilliant idea it's great it could work
in reality it still doesn't work so
while you have like I said institutions
taking the initiative and changing
things and it's kind of that whole thing
of tiny drops make a mighty ocean it
it'll get there eventually there's still
a lot of work to be done I still think
that um
meritocracy
is a double-edged sword and it's a sword
that doesn't actually work in the favor
of those that are most disadvantaged in
my opinion why
because ultimately it places this
emphasis on that if I do something on
Merit if I paid a freight on every
single thing I'm supposed to do then I
should get to where I'm supposed to now
that's a very simplistic version of
meritocracy but just humor me
what we know is that there are
intersectional inequalities that mean
that somebody can do all of those things
and based on their gender based on their
sexuality based on their religion based
on their race based on their class that
may impede them from in fact
utilizing or kashmi and cashing in that
meritocracy
so those things still exist and until
those things don't exist
until we can kind of which you know who
knows if will happen in our lifetime
mental you can eradicate those in with
those kind of inequalities
or those disadvantages in some respects
then maybe meritocracy will never
fulfill its true purpose
um but in reality with those things
still in The Ether it doesn't actually
it doesn't actually work
um because
if that's the case there are millions of
people who on Merit should be in a
position I'm in
now if we're saying that they're not
there because they're not good enough
obviously I don't entertain that but
what I do know is that the most
significant reason why we have for
example 162 black professors in the UK
of which just under 60 are black women
is because of how inequitable these
systems are and most of the black women
that reside in Academia
if not all of them are truly exceptional
yet we have a system in place
that subjugates them and doesn't allow
them to follow the Arc of that
trajectory to more senior levels whether
it be professorship whether it be you
know a vice Chancellor etc etc now based
on Merit if meritocracy really worked
those individuals would be the positions
they're supposed to be in but they're
not
and you know
of course there'll be people who turn
around and they'll argue and they'll say
well Jason is this reason you know it's
because this and this and this but
actually
like
you know if you if you don't if you're
not interested in anything else I say
just look at look at the facts
look at the facts you know and that's
and that that's a very important thing
because this idea meritocracy I think we
can we can often drift into this idea of
you know
oh these people you know if they did
what they were supposed to do then
they'd get this and I'm talking across
the insect generally speaking but it's a
real thing you know it this might be
shock to people but you can do
everything you're supposed to do
and you don't get a position based on
the intersections that I've I've
outlined now someone might turn around
and say well life isn't fair that's just
part of life well yeah I think we can
all accept that but we can all accept
that when it's just and it's fair
you know when it's not just in its fair
and it's underpinned by things that are
actually out of your control for example
potentially being a wheelchair user not
getting the job on the basis of ableism
then then no it's not fair if it was
just luck for everybody then that would
be a Level Playing then it'd be a level
playing but it's not and it also
suggests that we all start somehow from
the same start line when we don't
if you could change the world in any way
how would you change it
I would take
thread and a needle and I'd interweave
love into our society
that's what I would do I I think the
absence of love in our society is
absolutely palpable I feel like the
empathy we have for one another the
tolerance that we have from it's
completely eroded
you know and there is so much anger
in society
there's so much anger in society and I
often think what would one replace that
with
because also that anger has become
inflicted you know we're not we're not
kind of driven towards one goal we're
kind of turning on one another
and so for me the thing that I would do
if I could change the world
I would
have the world and I'd have it spinning
on this axis of love that's what I'd
have
um because we've lost as a society in my
humble opinion I think we've lost our
way and I think the last 15 years or the
last 13 years for sure
particularly in British Society has been
a huge enabler of that you know and I
think
the essence of Love might seem like a
very underrated thing or a very
melancholic thing
but it's really important because if I
said to you provide me examples of where
you see that in our daily Society you
know if I turn on news apart from the
kind of fun item that comes on at the
end
at the moment there's so much kind of
pulling us apart and very rarely do I
hear people talk about what the things
we could do to bring one another
together I mean is love a difficult word
for that you know because you know the
idea of love
not in the context of
a relationship or family
it's kind of lost all its meaning I mean
you know love meant something maybe in
the 1960s in the summer of love and all
that kind of stuff
that doesn't exist anymore are you you
know is that where you want to go back
you know these things are cyclical no
they are they are do we want another
sort of hippie 60s I mean look you look
let's be clear you're talking to a
hippie so of course I'm probably going
to lean towards that and I'm eternally
idealistic and optimistic and it's not
so much the love of
um The Summer of Love in the 60s it's
more about how we Center these things
as an axis to think about things like
empathy care compassion understanding
you know it's using that as a lever to
draw on those things that I've mentioned
so that we can think about how we can do
things collectively again
and I think love is a good framework to
work from to facilitate other things
because fundamentally
if we don't find a way to arrest
this kind of hate division this this
fear-mongering this all of these things
that are kind of really interfusing kind
of our lexicon our thinking our ways of
being
how often do you come across people who
actually speak from a sense of
positivity you know this is the thing I
think we've all forgotten that we all
have the capacity to do great and
wonderful things
we've we've lost our belief in one
another and for me it's important that
we regain that belief and move towards a
desired purpose because twitching
fingers don't really get you anywhere
but when you're a collective in your
penetrative fist you can really punch
through anything and now more than ever
we need that penetrative fist to punch
through all the inequalities and all the
kind of global difficulties that we are
currently facing in the 21st century
Society Jason alde thank you very much
indeed thank you very much Kristen